I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that a single
meal high in saturated fat
can impair artery function
for hours after consumption?
Here’s our first story.
We are only as old as our arteries.
What can we do to preserve
artery function as we age?
A poor diet and sedentary behavior
can lead to adverse aging processes,
like impairment of the little power
plants in our cells, which can result
in free radical formation, oxidative
stress, and inflammation, which leads
to artery dysfunction that can end in
the cardiovascular disease that ends us.
In a series of videos I did
about a decade ago,
I discussed this landmark research
showing that a single high-fat meal
could cripple artery function
within hours of consumption,
compared to no change
in the low-fat meal.
The high-fat meal that so
crippled artery function included
Sausage and Egg McMuffins
from McDonald's.
How do we know the sausage,
egg, or cheese was to blame?
What about the crappy
carbs in the biscuits?
We know because the low-fat meal
that didn't impair artery function
was a sugary mess
of carby Frosted Flakes.
And just when your artery
function finally starts to recover
five or six hours later?
Lunch time,
when your arteries may get
whacked with another load
of meat, eggs, dairy, or oil.
Why does it matter so much what
happens after a meal within your body?
Because most of us spend about 16
hours a day in that after-a-meal state,
constantly hammering our arteries.
No wonder cardiovascular
disease is our #1 killer.
And it doesn't just inflame the arteries
in our heart, but our lungs as well.
A high-fat challenge increases
airway inflammation
and impairs bronchodilator
recovery in asthma.
Have asthmatics cough up sputum
from their lungs four hours
after the same kind of high-fat
meal and inflammatory cells
shoot up in the high-fat meal group.
In terms of lung function, give
them two hits of their inhalers,
containing a drug called albuterol or
Ventolin, and their airways open up
as they should after the low-fat meal.
But after the high-fat meal, the same
inhaler doses don't work as well,
crapping out after a few hours
because of all the extra inflammation
in their lungs.
What you eat can determine
how well you breathe.
Okay, but that was asthmatics.
But even in nonasthmatic subjects,
you get the same spike
in inflammatory cells
in sputum coughed out of your lungs
four hours after eating what was,
in this case, a Jimmy Dean's
Meat Lovers breakfast bowl.
And there aren't only more
inflammatory cells; there's also
a doubling of the amount of
pro-inflammatory oxidized bad
LDL cholesterol sucked up
by the type of white blood cells
that go on to form foam cells.
Those are the cells that build up
the inflamed pus in your artery
wall that leads to heart attacks.
And all this happens within just
hours of eating pizza in this case.
The fat in your blood goes up
and so do your endotoxin levels.
Endotoxins are components
of bacterial cell walls,
and foods like meat can be so
contaminated with bacteria—
alive and dead—that they
accumulate endotoxins,
and we're talking about both
red meat and white meat.
But recent research published in
2020 suggests the main culprit
may not be endotoxins
after all, but the fat itself.
The saturated fat floating in your
blood after an unhealthy meal
may be inducing the inflammation
more directly. Either way,
we are accountable for
what we eat meal-by-meal
for the modification of the risk factors
for chronic metabolic disease.
In our next story, we look
at the window of time
in which sufficient physical
activity can help mediate
some of the damage caused
by eating an unhealthy meal.
In my last video, I discussed
studies that show a single meal
high in saturated fat can impair artery
function in men, as measured in the arm,
but what we're more concerned about
is blood flow to the wall of the heart.
Researchers randomized men to
eat either a high-fat meal that was
more than 60% fat, half of it saturated,
with more than an egg's worth
of cholesterol, or a low-fat
meal that was mostly carbs
with less than 10% fat and
50 times less cholesterol.
If part of a coronary artery
is blocked for any reason,
the surrounding vessels expand.
That extra expansion capacity is
called the coronary flow reserve,
and it's clamped down within
hours of eating a fatty meal,
undermining the heart's ability to
compensate for clogged arteries.
That's how a high-fat meal
affects blood flow to the heart.
What happens if you exercise, though,
right after that high-fat meal?
After-the-meal inflammation
following the prolonged elevation
of fat in the blood that occurs
when you eat high-fat meals,
provides a likely explanation for
increased cardiovascular disease.
But substantial evidence has
shown that acute exercise is
an effective modality for clearing
out some of that fat after a meal.
However, the benefits of acute
exercise for postprandial lipemia,
for after-the-meal fatty blood,
appear to be relatively short-lived.
Going a few days without exercising
may completely negate any benefit,
no matter how fit you are.
The time window appears to be
between 18 hours before the meal,
up until around 90 minutes
after the meal.
And how much exercise do we need?
About an hour of moderate-intensity
exercise should do it.
In this study though, it only took
20 minutes of stair climbing,
broken up into five minutes
every hour for four hours
after a McDonald's breakfast
of hash browns, eggs, pancakes,
muffins, sausage, and a milkshake.
Following such a meal, artery
function significantly decreased
when the subjects just
sat around after eating,
but not when they did the
hourly stair-climbing exercises.
In conclusion, hourly exercise may
attenuate the negative effects
not only of prolonged sitting but
also of high-fat meal intake,
suggesting that stair climbing
should be incorporated
as an easily accessible lifestyle
strategy to protect artery function.
Of course, it goes without saying
that the other way you can
protect artery-function is not
to eat breakfast at McDonald's
in the first place.
Such a meal would
also have more than
2,000 mg of sodium—more than the
1,500 the American Heart Association
recommends you stay
under for the entire day.
Give someone a meal with
even less salt, a third less,
and that alone can still impair artery
function within an hour of consumption,
even independent of the
increase in blood pressure.
When it comes to blood pressure,
some people are salt-sensitive,
meaning they suffer a large bump
in blood pressure when they eat salt.
But others are said to be salt-resistant.
Their blood pressure doesn't really
depend much on their salt intake.
So for these people is salt okay?
No. High dietary sodium intake
reduces artery function regardless
of whether your blood pressure
is salt-sensitive or salt-resistant.
Your artery function
is impaired either way,
going from a low salt diet
to a high salt diet.
See, there's an influence of dietary
salt beyond blood pressure.
In spite of the seemingly unanimous
consensus, some researchers—
too often funded by the salt industry—
claim that it's actually not good
to cut down on salt, but the evidence
is against these dissenters.
Like the saturated fat
in meat, dairy, and junk,
the science indicates that sodium,
not sodium reduction,
is the real villain.
Finally today, if you’re going
to eat something unhealthy,
is there anything you
can pair it with
to help mediate the
damage it may cause?
If you compare the artery function
of those who don't eat meat
to those who do, the healthy
ability of arteries to dilate and
let more blood flow is significantly
better among those eating vegetarian.
And not just by a little.
We're talking four times better.
Well, duh, vegetarians tend to be
younger, smoke less, be slimmer,
and have lower rates of diabetes,
high cholesterol, high blood pressure,
and heart disease. But the
researchers controlled for all that.
They only let healthy
nonsmokers into the study,
and recruited a group of meat eaters
who were just about as slim,
on average, and had about
the same blood pressures,
even practically the
same cholesterol—
a really healthy cohort
of omnivores—
yet they still got their arteries
handed to them by the vegetarians.
And the longer someone
was meat-free, the better.
The degree of superior artery
function correlated
with the number of years
eating meat-free.
Instead of their artery function
worsening over time as they aged,
it got better the longer
they ate that way.
This suggests that vegetarian
diets, by themselves,
have a direct beneficial effect
on artery function and may help
to account for the lower incidence
of atherosclerosis and
cardiovascular mortality.
Since researchers were able to
control for other known risk factors,
they figured it must be the food.
But what aspect of the food?
Is it simply the lack of the
deleterious effect of meat?
Or could it also be because the
vegetarians may simply be eating
more whole healthy
plant foods, for example,
up to a serving a day
more vegetables.
When researchers compared two crappy
meals, Sausage and Egg McMuffins
to Frosted Flakes, and found the
fatty meal impaired artery function
within hours but the sugary meal
didn't, they blamed the fat.
But it may just be the animal fat,
since high-fat whole plant foods
like nuts don't have the same effect.
In fact, if you look at
a systematic review
of all the randomized
controlled trials on the effect
of nut consumption
on artery function,
you find that nuts actually
make things better over time.
Enough to counter the artery-crippling
effects of a salami sandwich?
Let's find out. And the answer is
yes for walnuts, but no for almonds.
Just like there are some fruits
that are better than others,
like blueberries over bananas,
there are some nuts that are better
than others, and walnuts appear
to be the blueberries of nuts.
What about the blueberry of
berries: blueberries themselves?
A randomized, controlled crossover
trial of cooked blueberries,
raw blueberries, or
no blueberries at all.
If you feed people buns made out
of white flour, eggs, butter, and salt,
and fill them mostly
full of sugar and eggs,
you get a gradual drop in artery
function over the next six hours.
But add the equivalent of a cup of
wild blueberries to that same bun,
and instead you get a big
boost in artery function,
almost as if you had just mixed
the blueberries with water.
About the same amount of strawberries
failed to rescue artery function
from the likes of two cheese blintzes
with whipped cream, a sugary syrup,
egg and bacon, but that is
quite a heavy load to bear.
What about acai berries versus a
meal with a similar amount of fat?
One and a half-frozen smoothie packs
with half a small banana in water
were able to significantly
rehabilitate arterial function
compared to a control smoothie
with the same banana and water
colored to look like the acai one,
though obviously it would
have tasted differently.
This group of researchers went
all out, though, and performed
a double-blind randomized
controlled trial with raspberries,
measuring artery function after
2 hours and then 24 hours after
drinking about 3/4 of a cup of frozen
red raspberries blended with water,
or about a cup and a half,
versus a placebo drink meant
to match both color and taste.
The fake berry drink had no effect on
artery function, but the other two did.
Note the 3/4 cup dose
seemed to work just as well
as the cup and a half dose, which
is what you see with blueberries:
the benefits plateau
after about a cup.
The bottom line is that consumption
of dietarily achievable amounts of
red raspberries acutely improves
artery function for up to 24 hours.
You say, "Yeah, but by the end of the
day you're only up like one percent."
Ah, but at a population level, each
one percent increase is associated
with a 12% reduction in risk
of a cardiovascular event
like a heart attack or stroke, all
from just having a berry smoothie.
What about berry juice?
Five different concentrations
of cranberry juice were used,
along with a placebo control evidently
indistinguishable in color and taste.
The 25% cranberry juice drink
gave a little bump at two hours;
the 50% juice was still
working eight hours later.
The 75% juice, the one that was nearly
pure juice, and the ultra-concentrated
juice also improved artery function
within hours of consumption.
But this, like that last raspberry
study, just involved straight berries
without some artery-crushing meal.
Would berry juice be able
to stop artery dysfunction
caused by a high-fat
meal this unhealthy,
squeezing down artery
function within hours?
Researchers created a cocktail
of grapes, lingonberry, blueberry,
strawberry, and black aronia berry
and were able to turn this
into this. No significant change
after the high-fat meal.
Of course, if you had just
drunk those berries alone,
you'd probably get an improvement,
but it's better than nothing.
Well, what about something a little
less exotic than black aronia berries.
What about OJ?
Participants were provided a high-fat
meal of ham and cheese croissants,
along with either a cup of water,
orange juice, green tea, or red wine.
The arteries didn't much like the
croissants, and OJ was useless,
as was the green tea and red wine.
So it's probably best to not eat
ham and cheese croissants
in the first place.
In fact, drinking orange juice
with a fatty meal
could actually make things worse.
If you give people bacon and cheese
muffins with or without orange juice,
the OJ can lead to a prolongation
of elevated fat in the blood
as your body preferentially burns
for energy all the rapidly absorbed
free sugars in the juice, meaning
sugars not encased in cells walls,
as in those in whole fruit.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.